So today's דף daf is ל"ה Lamed He 35 and we are
actually more or less caught up. We pick up let's see if
we can keep on track. We pick up at the bottom of
ל"ד עמוד ב' Lamed Dalet Amud Bet and we are dealing with
the source of how we know that women are exempt from מצות
עשה שהזמן גרמא mitzvas asei shehazman grama and obligated from מצות עשה
שלא הזמן גרמא. mitzvas asei shelo hazman grama. And as one of
my students mentioned to me today who was yesterday who was doing
the דף, daf, he said, "It is so like convoluted how we
try to get it out and there's just as many exceptions as
there are things that fall into rule, and the question about why
do you use certain things as the paradigm and other things as
the exception and not vice versa, which is the question the גמרא
Gemara has." And you know then the גמרא's Gemara answer, it's not
like you're so overwhelmed by how persuasive the answer is.
And he said so this is really like they just really just
knew this and they were just going back and linking it to
פסוקים. pesukim. So I said, "You know what, that's exactly what רמב"ם
Rambam says." So and you know to remind us that רמב"ם Rambam
actually says not just that the כלל klal has exception, בין למדים
מן הכללות, bein lamadim min haklalos, but the רמב"ם Rambam actually says
against the simple sense of the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara seems
to feel like this rule מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא mitzvas asei shehazman
grama will really dictate and will really tell us about things that
we don't know what their status is, we just refer to the
rule unless we have something to teach us an exception, whereas רמב"ם
Rambam at the end of the day says you know we don't
know any of this stuff from a rule, we all just know
really everything from מסורה Mesora in terms of which things women are
obligated and which things women are exempt. So that deals in general
ראשונים Rishonim when the דרשה drasha seems to be not straightforward, it's
always a question: did חז"ל Chazal have a tradition about certain things
and they went back to find how it was based in the
פסוקים, pesukim, or did they start by not knowing and then they
said, "well let's derive it"? And the more
convoluted a link to the פסוקים pesukim is and the more it's
not at all clear what made you follow this path rather than
another path, the more ראשונים Rishonim say that that sounds like they
started with the tradition and they just went back to link it
to the פסוקים. pesukim. So that's worth I think as a way
of framing some of the issues we've been dealing with.
Anyway, have you
did you make mention of or do you think it's
worth, Saul Berman wrote a very well-known article many years ago on
precisely— yeah but that's a larger issue about women's status, so but
yes I mean he does very much address the issue about the
exemption of women from מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא mitzvas asei shehazman grama
and I think he deals with the רמב"ם Rambam as well. Actually
recently a woman I think just came out with her doctoral dissertation
was on the development of this in like חז"ל Chazal and the
various מדרשי הלכה Midreshei Halacha and so on about like this category
of the מצות mitzvos that women are obligated and exempt and מצות
עשה שהזמן גרמא. mitzvas asei shehazman grama. I think she discussed her
paper at like a recent JOFA conference. So there is obviously some
academic work on this, I don't remember her name. Anyway, so let's
just review where we are in the גמרא. Gemara. The case is
where we have a מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא, mitzvas asei shehazman grama,
okay let's see how good people's memory is, I had to erase
it because I had another class. Okay the cases where women are
פטור patur that we have in the פסוקים pesukim are תפילין. tefillin.
We of course mentioned the irony that this serves as the paradigm
even though what do you call it? Even though it's learned from
תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah and תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah is not in
the same category. Okay we have תפילין, tefillin, we have ראייה, re'iyah,
right, עולת ראייה, olat re'iyah, and what was the other one? How
good is anybody's memory?
תפילין Tefillin and ראייה. re'iyah.
There was a third one, wasn't there? הקהל. Hakhel. No הקהל Hakhel
is חייב. chayav. So in the חייב chayav category we have הקהל
Hakhel and we
have מצה. matzah. Okay and ד' כוסות, Dalet Kosos, no please, we
just דאורייתא. De-Oraisa.
Okay so
סוכה Sukkah was סוכה Sukkah where, right, סוכה Sukkah
was that they're פטור, patur, right, okay.
So what we said was basically the question became what which one
becomes the paradigm and which one becomes the exception? So the גמרא
Gemara said well this is the rule and this is the exception.
Well why why you say that? Why don't you say the reverse?
So it says well no these are שני כתובים הבאים כאחד. shnei
kesuvim habayim ke'echad. Since you know the basic principle is that if
it was the rule you would only need to say it once.
If you say it twice then it's obviously an exception because you're
pointing out the exception. So the גמרא Gemara says well this also
says it two or three times. Let these be the exceptions. So
says no no no. Here each one told you something. You needed
each one. Each one because what? Well סוכה Sukkah
we don't we needed because you would have said you would have
said what do you call it? You would have said תשבו כעין
תדורו teishvu ke'ein taduru and you would have thought that that's דוקא
davka reason to be מחייב, mechayav, so you needed to tell me
that that you're פטור. patur. Here needed to say because you would
have made a גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah to הקהל. Hakhel. Here you
would have told me what would you have said by תפילין? tefillin?
Oh
you would have linked it to... So each one of these you
would've had a reason to say חיוב chiyuv if it had pointed
it out. So the pointing out doesn't mean that it's an exception,
it was just to clarify that the rule is still in place.
Whereas here, the גמרא Gemara says, you didn't need to tell me
הקהל. Hakhel. You could've just told me that the infants are חייב
chayav in הקהל, Hakhel, and I would've known that the women are
חייב, chayav, and I could've learned it out from מצה, matzah, and
you wouldn't have had to tell me. So since הקהל Hakhel is
extra, okay, this is superfluous, that means that these are the שני
כתובים הבאים כאחד. sney kesuvim habayim ke'echad. That it's seen as that
they're not necessary,
they're not both necessary, and therefore this is the exception and this
is the rule. Okay, that's where we left off. So now we're
continuing at the bottom of ל"ד ע"ב. lamed-dalet amud-bet. The גמרא Gemara
says like this, did we cross out שמחה simcha for this one?
Because there were three originally. שמחה, simcha, right, thank you. שמחה simcha
is also not, is also because that's basically, well the גמרא Gemara
sort of said to some degree שמחה simcha is בעלה משמחה, ba'alah
mesamchah, so it's not so relevant. Thank you. Okay, good. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, הניחא, ha nicha, we pick up
like eight lines from the bottom, last word on the line, הניחא
ha nicha למאן דאמר אין מלמדין, le-man de-amar ein melamdin, that's good
if you say that when you have two cases that are set
explicitly, they're not the rule. אלא למאן דאמר מלמדין, ela le-man de-amar
melamdin, but there are some that say that no, even if the
תורה Torah gives you two examples, it's the rule. מאי איכא למימר?
mai ika le-meimar? What can you say? So okay, we have only
two examples here, let that be the rule. The fact that there's
one extra is not enough to say it's not the rule. So
if you say that even when you have שני כתובים הבאים כאחד
מלמדין, sney kesuvim habayim ke'echad melamdin, you still haven't told me why
the חייב chayav category is the exception, let the חייב chayav category
be the rule. That's question number one. ותו, ve-tu, question number two,
מצות עשה שלא הזמן גרמא נשים חייבות מנלן? mitzvas aseh she-lo hazman
grama nashim chayavos minalan? That's זמן גרמא. zman grama. How about שלא
זמן גרמא? she-lo zman grama? Where do you know the opposite rule?
Okay, how do you know the opposite rule that שלא זמן גרמא
she-lo zman grama that women are חייב? chayav? Maybe women should be
פטור. pattur. Okay, because there's also cases that fall in each category.
Okay, how do you know that? דיליף ממורא. de-yalif mi-mora.
You learn it from איש אמו ואביו תיראו ish imo ve-aviv tira'u
where it explicitly says, where we learn out, תיראו tira'u in the
plural means a man and a woman are חייב chayav in יראת
אב ואם. yiras av va-em. מה מורא נשים חייבות אף כל מצות
עשה שלא זמן גרמא נשים חייבות. mah mora nashim chayavos af kol
mitzvas aseh she-lo zman grama nashim chayavos. Okay, so how do you
know that they're חייב? chayav? Because it says
יראה yirah by אב ואם. av va-em.
Okay, that's how we know they're חייב. chayav. That's the rule. So
the גמרא's Gemara going to say, okay here, this is the rule
יראה yirah and this is the rule, right, this is the rule
that they're חייב. chayav. Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara going to say,
ונילף מתלמוד תורה, ve-neilaf mi-talmud torah, one minute, there are things that
are לאו זמן גרמא lav zman grama that women are פטור, pattur,
like תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. Let תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah be the
rule. Okay, we say this is the rule and this is the
exception. But how do you know? Let תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah be
the rule. ונילף מתלמוד תורה, משום דהוי תלמוד תורה ופריה ורביה שני
כתובים הבאים כאחד וכל שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין. ve-neilaf mi-talmud
torah, mishum de-havei talmud torah u-piryah ve-rivyah sney kesuvim habayim ke'echad ve-chol
sney kesuvim habayim ke'echad ein melamdin.
Same side of the answer, you also have פריה ורביה, piryah ve-rivyah,
ironically right, that that's the one that women are having the babies,
but based on the גמרא Gemara in יבמות Yevamos we say that
only men are obligated in פריה ורביה. piryah ve-rivyah. So we get
back to the same rule. How do we know that this is
the exception? Because there are two of them, and that makes it
the exception, and this makes it the rule because there's only one.
Of course we're going to see that's not going to be so
easy to say. So let's keep on reading. ורבי יוחנן בן ברוקא,
ve-Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka, top of ל"ה ע"א. lamed-hei amud-alef. דאמר על
שניהם הוא אומר ויברך אותם אלוהים ויאמר להם אלוהים פרו ורבו. de-amar
al sheneihem hu omer va-yivarech osam Elohim va-yomer lahem Elohim piru u-revu.
So he says that it
says ויברך אותם אלוהים ויאמר להם אלוהים פרו ורבו, va-yivarech osam Elohim
va-yomer lahem Elohim piru u-revu, women are obligated in פריה ורביה. piryah
ve-rivyah. So פריה ורביה, piryah ve-rivyah, God says to them פריה ורביה.
piryah ve-rivyah. So מאי איכא למימר? mai ika le-meimar? So you don't
have two, you only have one. And if you only have one,
let this be the rule. So the גמרא Gemara says, משום דהוי
תלמוד תורה ופדיון הבן שני כתובים הבאים כאחד. mishum de-havei Talmud Torah
u-Pidyon HaBen sney kesuvim habayim ke'echad. Remember
we learned earlier that women are exempt פדיון הבן, Pidyon HaBen, and
that once the kid hits thirty days, that's a מצוה mitzvah without
stop. It doesn't stop at night, it doesn't stop the whole life.
So that's a מצות עשה שלא הזמן גרמא. mitzvas aseh she-lo hazman
grama. So again, we have two cases, that makes it the exception.
Did we learn that specifically from other פסוקים? pesukim? פדיון הבן, Pidyon
HaBen, that that's why? No, no, we learned it from the fact
that it
said תפדה, tifdeh, תיפדה, tipadeh, מי שיש לו בפדיון, mi she-yesh lo
be-fidyon,
whatever, but not from, anyway whatever, we learned it from a פסוק.
pasuk. So
isn't that like an exception then because you learn it, oh תפדה,
tifdeh, תיפדה? tipadeh? Yeah, that's what we're saying. These are, I mean,
the fact that it said it means that they're exceptions. That's the
point. That's שני כתובים הבאים כאחד. sney kesuvim habayim ke'echad. That's exactly
why it's not a rule, because if it was a rule you
wouldn't have had to learn it from a פסוק. pasuk. That's the
logic of שני כתובים הבאים כאחד. sney kesuvim habayim ke'echad. Okay, so
therefore שני כתובים הבאים כאחד וכל שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין.
sney kesuvim habayim ke'echad ve-chol sney kesuvim habayim ke'echad ein melamdin. Fine.
Now the גמרא Gemara says, ורבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, ve-Rabbi Yochanan ben
Beroka, so we still have the question, we still haven't answered this,
right, that if you say you need that two פסוקים pesukim you
can be מלמד, melamed, why do you know which is the rule,
which is the exception? But working still with the idea that once
there's two פסוקים, pesukim, it's the exception. also explained that here as
well there's the exception. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute ולרבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא נמי הוי פרו ורבו ומורשה שני כתובים הבאים כאחד
ואין מלמדין. ul'Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka nami havei piru v'rivu u-morasha shnei
kesuvim habayim ke'echad v'ein melamdin. The גמרא Gemara says one minute, according
to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka, פרו ורבו pru
u'rvu moves to the other column, right? It's like right now we're
on election season. If you're voting for somebody else, it actually switches
two points of the line, right? So,
so when פרו ורבו pru u'rvu moves to this column, according to
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka, this becomes now the
exception. You also have two cases here. So why do you make
this the exception? Make this the exception. Okay,
צריכי. tzrichi. No, no, no. There, according to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא,
Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka, you would say you needed both cases to
be said explicitly, and if they're necessary to be said, they're not
the exception. דאי כתב רחמנא מורא ולא כתב פרו ורבו, de-i kasav
Rachmana mora v'lo kasav piru v'rivu, if it had said יראת אב
ואם, yiras av v'eim, הוה אמינא דחיובא אמר רחמנא, hava amina d'chiyuva
amar Rachmana, איש דרכו לכבוש ish darcho lichbosh ואין אשה דרכה לכבוש,
v'ein isha darcha lichbosh,
right? Anyway, it's לכבוש. lichbosh. Anyway, yeah,
so anyway, yeah, it's לכבוש, lichbosh, right? I know, so why's there
no ו vav there? Anyway, whatever. Okay, anyway, it used to pickle.
Okay, fine.
That's a good point. Okay, anyway, so the פסוק, pasuk, meaning where
do חז"ל Chazal know? רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka
makes such a powerful point that it says ויאמר להם אלהים פרו
ורבו, v'yomer lahem Elohim pru u'rvu, right? I mean, so how, how
do the rabbis answer back? Why is it only the man's obligation?
Because it says, right,
פרו
ורבו ומלאו את הארץ
וכבשה. pru u'rvu u-milu es ha-aretz v'chivshuha.
וכבשה. v'chivshuha.
So if it's supposed to be about, about sort of having dominion
over the land, settling the land, dominion, etc., you know, and this,
and this might even have a militaristic sense of, you know, whatever,
you know, seizing and conquering, conquering I guess is a good word.
So anyway, so obviously it says, that indicates that we're talking to
the man, because that's the type of thing that's assumed to be
like male behavior. So that indicates the פסוק pasuk is talking about
the man. ממש אחשוורוש, mamash Achashveirosh, וכל איש שורר בביתו. v'chol ish
sorer b'veiso. Right.
So therefore, the reason it had to say explicitly, it's a little
bit funny. The reason it had to say, I guess you would
say the reason it had to explicitly say that women are חייב
chayav in פרו ורבו, pru u'rvu, not that it had to say
פרו ורבו pru u'rvu because it's a מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו,
pru u'rvu, but the women, he had to make it clear, ויאמר
להם אלהים, v'yomer lahem Elohim, to spell it out explicitly, was because
you might have thought like the rabbis that וכבשה v'chivshuha meant only
men. So therefore, that was necessary to be said, and if it's
necessary, it's not an exception. That's why פרו ורבו pru u'rvu was
necessary to be said. Okay, אמר רחמנא איש דרכו לכבוש ואין אשה
דרכה לכבוש. amar Rachmana ish darcho lichbosh v'ein isha darcha lichbosh. No,
I would have thought that it only, that if it just said
מורא, mora, I would have said, I'm sorry, I think I jumped
that. I would have said that if it had just said מורא,
mora, I would have said it's only מורא mora and not פרו
ורבו pru u'rvu because of this דרכו לכבוש, darcho lichbosh, and I
said it right. So therefore, it had to say explicitly פרו ורבו
pru u'rvu that it's women as well, so I shouldn't make this
mistake. ואי כתב פרו ורבו, v'i kasav pru u'rvu, if it had
just said women are obligated in פרו ורבו, pru u'rvu, why couldn't
I have learned out יראת אב ואם yiras av v'eim from that?
ולא כתב מורא, v'lo kasav mora, הוה אמינא, hava amina, איש דסיפק
בידו לעשות, ish d'sipak beyado la'asos, אין, in, no, I would have
said that this is a, maybe this is a special case that
women should be exempt from יראת אב ואם. yiras av v'eim. Why?
Because men have a greater freedom of, you know, in a marriage,
greater sort of, they don't have a, you know, a sense of
greater sort of freedom of activity. And therefore they're obligated in יראת
אב ואם. yiras av v'eim. אשה דאין סיפק בידה לעשות, isha d'ein
sipak beyada la'asos, a woman who does not have that same latitude,
she has a primary responsibility at home to her husband and to
her kids, לא, lo, maybe the תורה Torah would have exempted her
from
יראת אב ואם. yiras av v'eim. So, since her times she's not
able to do it, לא תיחייב כלל, lo tichayev klal, maybe she'd
get a straight, a total exemption. צריכה, tzricha, it needs to say.
So the גמרא Gemara says, oh, according to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא,
Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka, having two here does not make this the
exception because each one is necessary. I shouldn't have limited פרו ורבו
pru u'rvu to the man because of וכבשה. v'chivshuha. I shouldn't limit
יראת אב ואם yiras av v'eim to the man because he has
more freedom of activity. So it had to say it, and the
fact that it was necessary to say it means that it's the
rule and not the exception. Okay, so we've got nothing then. What?
So there's no rule, there's no nothing? Exactly. That's,
these mean these are special exceptions. No, they have independent reasons. So
how can you cluster them?
As long as it's the other point. The fact that it's said
presumes that it's going to be the rule. It only becomes the
exception if we see that it having been said was superfluous. Okay,
anytime anything is said once, we presume it's the rule. Unless we
start realizing that the תורה Torah is saying it more than necessary,
and then we see it as an exception. So the fact that
it says that a woman is חייב chayav makes us infer that
that's the rule. Don't say that this is repeated unnecessarily, because there's
a reason to say it in all the cases. Whereas here it's
understood that the fact that, that it was unnecessary to say it
in both places, right? If this were the rule, it wouldn't have
had to be said both by תלמוד תורה talmud Torah and פדיון
הבן. pidyon haben. And the fact that it said in both cases
teaches us that it's not the rule, that it's the exception. Okay?
So again, same point. Yes. There are a lot of things that
fall into both categories, but we're arguing that here it's superfluous, some
of the cases are not necessary, it makes it the exception. Here
everything is necessary, it's the rule. And we say the same thing
down here in the other cases. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
continues.
So where were we? וכיון דאי איכא לא. vekeyvan de'ei icha lo.
Okay, כלל. klal. הא ניחא Ha nicha
now, back to the question though, fine, you basically gave the same
answer for both, that there are cases in both columns, but some
of them are superfluous and if they're superfluous and there are two
cases, we say that they're the exception and not the rule. But
that's only if you say that two cases prove something is an
exception. שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין. Shenei ketuvim habaim ke'echad ein
melamdin. Some people say שני כתובים מלמדין, shenei ketuvim melamdin, two cases
can still be a rule. So the גמרא Gemara says הא ניחא
למאן דאמר שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין. ha nicha leman de'amar
shenei ketuvim habaim ke'echad ein melamdin. That's good if you say that
you can't learn, that they're an exception once you have two cases
and at least there's something that's superfluous. אלא למאן דאמר מלמדין, Ella
leman de'amar melamdin, but if you say that even two cases and
even if it looks a little superfluous is still a rule, מאי
איכא למימר? mai ika lemeimar? What can you say? And that goes
on both the זמן גרמא zman grama and the לא זמן גרמא.
lo zman grama. You know, you have so what makes those cases
exceptions and not rules? So אמר רבא, amar Rava, פפונאי ידעי לה
לטעמא דהא מילתא. Papunai yadei lah leta'ama deha milta.
Those פפונאים, Papuniyim, there's apparently there was a place called פפונא, Papuna,
רש"י Rashi will tell us where that is, Chavel will tell us
where that is. Anyway, it's described by Steinsaltz, anyway. And
anyway, they know the answer to this. Why? Who is the people
from פפונא? Papuna? ומארי דאביי בר יעקב. Umarei de'avacha bar Yaakov. רב
אחא בר יעקב. Rav Achai bar Yaakov. So what does he say
the meaning is? How do we know these rules given all the
questions we just asked? אמר קרא: Amar kra: והיה לך לאות על
ידך ולזכרון בין עיניך למען תהיה תורת ה' בפיך. vehaya lecha le'ot
al yadecha ulezikaron bein eineicha lema'an tihye Torat Hashem befecha. הוקשה כל
התורה כולה לתפילין. Huksha kol hatorah kullah letfillin. Okay. מה תפילין מצות
עשה שהזמן גרמא נשים פטורות אף כל מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא נשים
פטורות. Mah tfillin mitzvat aseh shehazman grama nashim peturot af kol mitzvat
aseh shehazman grama nashim peturot.
So you know what, you're right. There are too many exceptions, too
many things mentioned in each category. If you were just looking at
this list, you would have no idea which is the rule and
which is the exception. Okay, at least we can concede that. Okay,
there's things that fall in both categories in both זמן גרמא zman
grama and לא זמן גרמא. lo zman grama. At the end of
the day, it's not because oh this has two and this doesn't
have two or whatever. Fine, forget that. Anyway, even if it had
two probably you could maybe still make the argument either way. The
argument still is back to our friend תפילין. tfillin. Since it ends
by saying למען תהיה תורת ה' בפיך, lema'an tihye Torat Hashem befecha,
it means that this is a paradigm for כל התורה כולה. kol
hatorah kullah. And therefore, since תפילין tfillin is מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא
mitzvat aseh shehazman grama and women are פטורות, peturot, and it links
it to תורה, Torah, that פסוק pasuk is telling you that תפילין
tfillin is the paradigm. Okay. So how do we know from the
תורה Torah that תפילין tfillin is מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא? mitzvat aseh
shehazman grama? Oh,
that's from the link to תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah where we exclude
where we exclude, you know, בניכם ולא בנותיכם, beneichem velo benoteichem, right?
But it's ironic because תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah itself is בניכם ולא
בנותיכם beneichem velo benoteichem and that doesn't become the rule, that's not
linked to כל התורה כולה kol hatorah kullah and only תפילין tfillin
is linked to כל התורה כולה. kol hatorah kullah. Anyway, so let's
just read it. מה תפילין מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא ונשים פטורות אף
כל מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא נשים פטורות. Mah tfillin mitzvat aseh shehazman
grama venashim peturot af kol mitzvat aseh shehazman grama nashim peturot. So
it's not based on how many things are in each list. It's
the fact that the תורה Torah labels תפילין tfillin as representative of
כל התורה כולה. kol hatorah kullah.
And now we say ומי דמצות עשה שהזמן גרמא נשים פטורות, umi
de'mitzvat aseh shehazman grama nashim peturot, and now we can just infer
the converse, since this is the rule, and the point is it
should be the rule for כל התורה כולה, kol hatorah kullah, so
why did the תורה Torah pick the rule of כל התורה כולה
kol hatorah kullah something that's a time-bound מצוה mitzvah to say women
are exempt, right? It must be that we should infer that it's
only the unique characteristics of תפילין tfillin that make women exempt because
it's time-bound, but something that wouldn't be in that category,
women would be חייבות. chayavot. ומי דמצות עשה שהזמן גרמא נשים פטורות
מכלל דמצות עשה שלא זמן גרמא נשים חייבות. Umi de'mitzvat aseh shehazman
grama nashim peturot michlal de'mitzvat aseh shelo zman grama nashim chayavot. Okay.
Phew. That was a lot easier than figuring out all
these lists. Bottom line, תפילין, tfillin, תפילין tfillin is the source, end
of story. Now let's now let's let's see can we
end with that? Let's keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: הא ניחא למאן דאמר תפילין מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא. Ha
nicha leman de'amar tfillin mitzvat aseh shehazman grama. Oh, יישר כוח, shkoach,
if it's a time-bound מצוה. mitzvah. אלא למאן דאמר תפילין מצות עשה
שלא זמן גרמא מאי איכא למימר? Ella leman de'amar tfillin mitzvat aseh
shelo zman grama mai ika lemeimar? Okay. Because if you say it's
obligated at night and on שבת, Shabbos, and there are those opinions,
so then what can you say? So then great, let it be
the paradigm and let it say that women are exempt from all
מצות עשה. mitzvos aseh. So the גמרא Gemara says רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. So the גמרא Gemara says no. מאן שמעת ליה דאמר תפילין
מצות עשה שלא זמן גרמא? Man shama'at lei de'amar tfillin mitzvat aseh
shelo zman grama? Who is the one that says that תפילין tfillin
applied both at night and on שבת Shabbos and it's not זמן
גרמא? zman grama? רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. We know from another גמרא
Gemara that that's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Okay. וסבר לה, Vesavar lah,
but we also know that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is of the
opinion that שני כתובים הבאים כאחד, shenei ketuvim habaim ke'echad, that once
you have two פסוקים, pesukim, they're the exception and not the rule.
וכל שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין. Vekol shenei ketuvim habaim ke'echad
ein melamdin. So we go back because in the end of the
day remember what we said is we managed to say that bottom
line is in the category... categories of exception have two cases which
and are seen as superfluous, both in this category of שהזמן גרמא
shehazman grama and הזמן גרמא, hazman grama, and therefore these become the
exception. And the categories of חיוב, chiyuv, although they also have more
than one case, all of those were necessary. But because these were
superfluous, these become the exceptions. And the Gemara said, but there's only
two in each column. And some people say even with two cases,
you can have it as the rule and not the exception. And
that led us to say okay, okay, it's all about תפילין. tefillin.
What about those that say you can't learn that תפילין tefillin is
לא זמן גרמא? lo zman grama? Fine, that's Rabbi Meir. And Rabbi
Meir says that two cases does label something as an exception. So
basically we have two לימודים: limudim: either two cases labels it as
an exception, and that's true here, and here they're not seen as
extra, therefore that's you don't apply the same principle. Or if you
need more than two cases to label something as an exception, you
can use תפילין tefillin as your paradigm for כל התורה כולה. kol
hatorah kullah. And now the Gemara just ends this and says the
following. ורבי יהודה דאמר שני כתובים הבאים כאחד
מלמדין. veRabbi Yehuda de'amar shnei kesuvim haba'im ke'echad melamdin. Wait, but we
got a problem. Because number one Rabbi Yehuda says that two cases
are can be a rule, not an exception. Okay? And he says
ותפילין מצות עשה שלא הזמן גרמא. vetefillin mitzvat asseh shelo hazman grama.
So what happens if you have neither path available to you? Rabbi
Yehuda says תפילין tefillin is not time bound. So that can't be
the paradigm. And he also says two cases can be a rule,
not an exception. So if two if תפילין tefillin is can't be
the paradigm, and if two cases can be a rule, what makes
you pick one column over the other column? Back to the question.
So the Gemara says משום דהוי מצה ושמחה והקהל שלושה כתובים הבאים
כאחד ושלושה כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין mishum dehvei matzah vesimcha vehakhel
shlosha kesuvim haba'im ke'echad veshlosha kesuvim haba'im ke'echad ein melamdin
because we would once again put שמחה simcha back on the list,
we would not say what we said before that שמחה simcha is
basically the husband's obligation, שמחה simcha is the wife's obligation. So we
have three cases on the list, and if we have three cases
on the list, that labels it as the exception. How about up
here? Well maybe if we would have פרו ורבו, peru urevu, we
would also have three cases on this list. Okay? So there are
basically now three ways to say I mean two and a half
ways to say how we know it. Either תפילין tefillin is the
paradigm, end of story, תפילין tefillin is time bound. Or תפילין tefillin
is not time bound and isn't the paradigm, then the point is
fine. But ironically, there are so many times the Torah explicitly labels
things that go against the rule, both here and here, three cases
that go against this rule and three cases that go against this
rule, that that labels these as the exceptions. Okay? And because all
the explicit cases that were against the rule, from there we know
that the rule is the opposite. Okay? Which is of course very
ironic. Okay. Alright, anyway, moving on. We are now done with how
we know מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא mitzvat asseh shehazman grama women are
פטור patur and לא זמן גרמא lo zman grama women are חייב.
chayav. And now we get to the next part of the משנה.
mishnah. לא תעשה. lo ta'asseh. Right. How do you לא תעשה lo
ta'asseh men and women are חייב, chayav, except for a handful like
טומאת כהנים tumas kohanim and בל תקיף bal takif of the of
the פאות peios and of the of the beard. Okay, so now
let's move to that. וכל מצות לא תעשה vechol mitzvot lo ta'asseh
women are women are exempt. Oh women are חייב. chayav. מנא הני
מילי, mena hanei milei, where do you know this from? אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav וכן תנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל vechen tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael אמר קרא איש או אשה כי
יעשו מכל חטאת האדם. amar kra ish o isha ki ya'asu mikol
chatos ha'adam. Okay? And that talks about bringing a קרבן korban when
it's a certain case of like of גזל הגר, gezel hager, but
nevertheless the framing of it מכל חטאת האדם, mikol chatos ha'adam, all
types of sins, and speaks about their, you know, liability towards it.
So because it's used that generic phrase, it shows that anything that's
a sin, meaning not just an omitting of a positive מצוה, mitzvah,
but a transgression, is something that applies to איש או אשה. ish
o isha. השוה הכתוב אשה לאיש לכל עונשים שבתורה. hishva haksav isha
le'ish lechol onashim shebatorah. All types
of punishments and transgressions that are deserving of punishment apply equally to
men and women. How do you know that's a לא תעשה lo
ta'asseh though? If I could do a if I don't do the
פסח, pesach, that could be מצות עשה. mitzvat asseh. Yeah, so I
mean it's I mean it's a good point. I mean, you know,
but again I think that the general sense is that a חטא
cheit has to do with an action that is a transgression, not
a lack of performing of an obligation. I mean that's the yeah
that's the presumption that's going here.
Yeah. Anyways, so now the Gemara says דבי רבי... d'vei Rabbi... now
we could have just ended there, but we normally have a whole
little package of לימודים limudim that teaches me the scope of women
things that women are obligated in. Our משנה mishnah just addressed מצות
לא תעשה, mitzvot lo ta'asseh, but this following like 10 lines of
גמרא gemara is like appears in multiple different places in ש"ס Shas
and it's just a like three different לימודים limudim to tell me
all different things that women are חייב chayav in. So we're now
going to go on even though it's beyond the scope of our
משנה. mishnah. Okay, so it says like this. דבי רבי אליעזר תנא,
d'vei Rabbi Eliezer tana, from the house of Rabbi Eliezer they taught,
אמר קרא אשר תשים לפניהם. amar kra asher tasim lifneihem. These are
the משפטים mishpatim that you will place before them, with an emphasis
on משפטים, mishpatim, like the civil laws. So השוה הכתוב hishva haksav
and לפניהם lifneihem is collective, all of them, right? So therefore השוה
הכתוב אשה לאיש לכל דינים שבתורה. hishva haksav isha le'ish lechol dinim
shebatorah. So all matters of civil law, right? of sort of בין
אדם לחבירו, bein adam lachaveiro, of loaning and you know... property and
damages and theft and all those types of issues, all matters of
civil law. So all matters of criminal law apply equally to men
and women; that's ככל חטאת האדם kechol chatot ha'adam and all matters
of civil law apply equally to men and women. Does this even
have to do with me though, right? Right, right. No, right, this
is just the question about like how do I know that if
my ox gores you, I've got to pay? If it gores a
woman's ox, it's got to pay. If a woman's ox gores me,
it's got... how do I know those types of things? Okay. So
דבי חזקיה תנא, devei Chizkiyah tana, from the house of Chizkiyah they
taught, אמר קרא, amar kra, והמית איש או אשה. v'hemit ish o
isha. Later in משפטים, Mishpatim, it speaks about an ox that gores
and kills a man or a woman and has to do a
כופר, kofer, right? This sort of atonement payment. So why does it
say איש או אשה? ish o isha? השוה הכתוב אשה לאיש לכל
מיתות שבתורה. Hishvah hakatuv isha l'ish l'chol mitot shebatorah. Any... if a
woman is a victim of murder or of a goring of an
ox or whatever, the then the punishment and the, you know, is
equally severe, it's treated as equal. Okay, so three different ways in
which the תורה Torah is saying women have the same are in
the same legal status as men. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: וצריכא, utzricha, it needed all three cases. דאי אשמעינן הך
קמייתא, de'i ashmi'inan hach kamaisa, if it had just talked about transgression,
that women are punished for transgression, משום
כפרה, mishum kaparah, חסה רחמנא עלה. chasah rachmana alah. So maybe, now
of course it's a little ironic, because maybe in order because that
the תורה Torah said that women get punished for their transgression as
much as men because the sense is that punishment serves as an
atonement for the transgression. Of course the question is, but but, you
know, it's funny because of the first thing you see you would
have to teach me is first tell me that they are that
they are bound by those negative prohibitions, right? But anyway, so it's
like so it was well, that's only there because to give them
כפרה, kaparah, right? I mean the first but you know the חידוש
chiddush is before that they get כפרה kaparah for being punished is
that they're bound by the prohibition. But anyway, if it had just
said that, I would have said maybe you can't infer from that
that women are are equal in other places of the law, because
maybe it's only in areas of transgression. I mean we could flip
it. Transgression is particularly weighty because it's transgression and they get punished
because to give them כפרה kaparah for transgression. But you couldn't have
inferred from that to give them necessarily equal standing when it came
to civil law. All right.
So where are we? חסה רחמנא עליה. chasah rachmana aleiha. אבל דינים,
aval dinim, when it came to civil law, אימא איש eima ish
דבר משא ומתן, de'bar masa umatan, אין. in. Maybe a man that
normally is the one who does business, maybe that's the guy that
the תורה Torah sort of applied all the laws of civil law
to. אשה לא, isha lo, and a woman not, which is ironic
because just because she's not usually in that category doesn't mean that
when she does find herself in that category she should be disadvantaged
or whatever. But not maybe nevertheless, maybe that's a way of keeping
her out of that category. We only want men to do business
and therefore these laws, I don't know. Anyway, so one might have
thought that, that a woman does not have equal standing in civil
law. ואי אשמעינן הא, ve'i ashmi'inan ha, if it had just told
me a woman has equal has equal standing in civil law, משום
דחיושא היא, mishum de'chiyusa hi, because it's necessary for her livelihood. As
רש"י Rashi says, if you didn't have any standing in civil law,
somebody could rob from her and steal from her and and borrow
money and not pay back and would be exempt. And she could
do the same. She could rob and, you know, from somebody else
and not be obligated. So basically it would make her like a
pariah in civil society. Okay? If she was not had equal treatment
under the law. So it was necessary. אבל כופר, aval kofer, so
now we have necessary for types of of what do you call
it, of like sins because, you know, it's weighty, so she's bound
by it and she needs a form of atonement if she transgresses.
We have the issue about business because it's necessary to be part
of society be bound by civil law. אבל כופר, aval kofer, but
the idea that if an ox gores it pays atonement, אימא... eima...
Okay, this has got to be one of the most difficult lines
that we're going to read. אימא איש דבר מצות, eima ish de'bar
mitzvos, אין. in.
Maybe an ox only has to pay כופר kofer when it gores
a man because a man is like obligated in מצוות. mitzvos. אשה
isha דלאו בת מצות... de'lav bas mitzvos... No, that's what תוספות Tosafot
adds. תוספות Tosafot says דלאו בת מצות. de'lav bas mitzvos. I mean
we just got through saying that women are obligated מצות עשה שלא
הזמן גרמא. mitzvos asei she'lo hazman grama.
Anyway, אשה, isha, but a woman who has less of a מצוה
mitzvah obligation, לא, lo, maybe, you know, would not be. Is that
right? Is that like like she's not considered a בר מצות? bar
mitzvos? Like it's rather arbitrary. Like since when do we see that
the killing is because of the number of מצוות? mitzvos? I understand.
And then if it kills an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, he has
fewer מצוות? mitzvos? Well no, he's not bound by fewer מצוות. mitzvos.
That's not about that's not about his legal status. But this is
look, this is obviously very difficult because, you know, רב משה פיינשטיין
Rav Moshe Feinstein was asked once in the earlier ages of feminism,
I don't remember, going back 40 years, 50 years, you know, about
a rabbi that said, you know, women in my community are basically
saying that the תורה Torah recognizes sees them, you know, as second-class
citizens, sees that they don't have the same level of not just
that they don't do as many מצוות mitzvos as men, but that
in a fundamental way their status, they're recognized as... Same with their
humanity. Well right, they're recognized as less קדושה, kedusha, less of a
status, and so on. And you know, we make a ברכה שלא
עשני אשה beracha she'lo asani isha and the whole thing. So he
goes through this whole תשובה tshuvah and says no, חס ושלום, chas
v'shalom, that's absolutely not true. Same level of קדושה, kedusha, everything. everything
is the same, it's just technically there are reasons why they're פטור
מצוות patur mitzvot but that doesn't see them as fundamentally of a
different status, okay? But you know you then read like a גמרא
Gemara like this, you could see it's only the הווא אמינא hava
amina and in the end it rejects the הווא אמינא, hava amina,
right? But it sort of says that well, maybe we should look
from the exemption of מצוות, mitzvot, that would have put them at
some lower status and therefore not as deserving as an atonement payment
if they get killed by an ox. A very, very disturbing גמרא.
Gemara. And yeah, does this connect with the question of how much
we're considering a
wife property, the discussion earlier?
Yeah, but that was as sexual property. I think that was still
less. It never quite got to the conversation of sort of like
as a slave of property, you know, in that sort of sense.
But there might be an element. Yeah, I mean maybe there's, yeah,
I mean yeah,
maybe there could be. The thing is the woman has more מצוות
mitzvot than men because
what do you mean? Because
they're raising the children. Right. In practice that's of course the irony
as well. I mean that's of course the irony as well, which
is like as a matter of, you know, I mean as a
matter of like who really maintains the Jewish household, right, you know,
it's the women, right? כשרות kashrut and שבת Shabbat and raising the
kids and all of that. But then as a matter of like
social standing, right, the men are sort of seen in this higher
position, but that's an excellent point. Yeah. פשיטא. Pshita. Anyway, I would
have had a הווא אמינא, hava amina, ברוך השם Baruch Hashem that's
not the הלכה. halacha. פשיטא Pshita anyway, I would have had a
הווא אמינא hava amina משום דאיכא איבוד נשמה. mishum deika ibud neshama.
Just tell me that, we're talking about loss of life. So of
course women are going to be treated equally. חס רחמנא עלה. Chas
Rachmana alah. So therefore the Torah had רחמנות rachmanut and said you
know life, she's deserving of obviously or the heirs are deserving of
a כופר kofer payment. אבל הנך תרתי, Aval hanach tarti, other things
which are not as severe as loss of life, אימא לא, eima
lo, maybe women would not have equal treatment. צריכא, Tzricha, it needs
it. So at the end of the day, women are treated as
equal sort of, you know, citizens in all these areas, civil law,
criminal law, the whole thing. The only difference is certain time-bound certain
מצוות עשה. mitzvot asseh. Okay. And now we go with a small
number of negative מצוות mitzvot of prohibitions that women are exempt from.
חוץ Chutz with three exceptions. בל תקיף ובל תשחית, Bal takif uval
tashchit, cutting the פאות peyot and cutting the corners of the beard,
and טומאת כהנים. tumat kohanim. Okay, for a כהן, kohen, male כהנים
kohanim cannot become טמא למתים. tamei lametim. So the גמרא Gemara says
בשלמא bishlama about טמא למתים tamei lametim I get, it's obvious why
the becoming טמא למתים tamei lametim does not apply to women. דכתיב
Dechtiv אמור אל הכהנים בני אהרן, emor el hakohanim bnei Aharon, say
to the כהנים kohanim the sons of אהרן. Aharon. So בני אהרן
ולא בנות אהרן, bnei Aharon velo bnot Aharon, right? And it's not
just like a פסוק pasuk that's exempting, we know that basically the
male children are called כהנים. kohanim. You know what a female child
of a כהן kohen is called? בת כהן. bat kohen. Actually there
is one or two גמרות Gemarot that actually refer to her as
a כהנת. kohenet. Okay. And actually some discussion about whether you can
give a בת כהן bat kohen slash כהנת kohenet like the מתנות,
matanot, you know, like the זרוע ולחיים וקיבה, zeroa ulechayayim vekeiva, you
know, in certain things. Interesting. Anyway, but nevertheless, fundamentally not really recognized
as a כהן. kohen. Only the males are כהנים. kohanim. So clearly
that only applies to the males. Okay. אלא בל תקיף ובל תשחית,
Ella bal takif uval tashchit, but cutting the corners of the פאות
peyot of the head, you know, and the sidelocks and the beard,
מנלן, menalan, how do you know to exempt women? Right? And again,
you might say well women don't have those. Well first of all
women do have, you know,
could have some sidelocks. They don't have the beards, but some women
do have beards. I mean whatever. And and what about cutting somebody
else's beard, right? So how do you know that they are exempt
from that? So the גמרא Gemara says it says פאת זקנך? pe'at
zekanecha? Yeah. So
זקנך ולא זקנתך? zekanecha velo zekantecha? וזקנך, Vezekanecha, yours. Uh yeah, but
you transgress when you cut other people. I mean that's another discussion.
But you do transgress when you cut somebody else's beard. So anyway
the גמרא Gemara says מנלן, menalan, where do you know that women
are exempt? דכתיב לא תקיפו פאת ראשכם ולא תשחית את פאת זקנך.
Dechtiv lo takifu pe'at roshchem velo tashchit et pe'at zekanecha.
So, so כל שישנו בהשחתה ישנו בהקפה. kol sheyeshno behashchata yeshno behakafa.
Anybody that is prohibited against destroying the beard is prohibited to get
is, you know, prohibited to cut off the sidelocks. והני נשי הואיל
ולא איתנהו בהשחתה, Vehani neshei ho'il velo itnehu behashchata, since women are
not, you know, warned against cutting the corners of the beard, ליתנהו
בהקפה, leitnehu behakafa, they're also not warned against the sidelocks. So now
the גמרא Gemara says how do you know? How do you know
they're not warned against the beard? ומנלן דלא איתנהו בהשחתה? Umenalan delo
itnehu behashchata? How do you know they're not? And רש"י Rashi says
let's say they happen to have facial hair and have a beard,
or as I I say let's say it's for cutting somebody else's
beard. Anyway, how do you know they're not included in the cutting
of the beard? So the גמרא Gemara says
ומנלן דלא איתנהו בהשחתה, umenalan delo itnehu behashchata, אי בעית אימא ei
ba'it eima if you want סברא, sevara, דלאו אית לה זקן. delav
itla zakan. It's just סברא. sevara. Clearly, okay, you can have some
rare exception that maybe you know a woman has a beard, but
nevertheless clearly the תורה Torah is talking to men, right? That's the
presumed audience here, you know? So that's number one. ואי בעית אימא,
Vei ba'it eima, if you want I can tell you קרא, kra,
it's from the פסוק, pasuk, דאמר קרא לא תקיפו פאת ראשכם ולא
תשחית את פאת זקנך. de'amar kra lo takifu pe'at roshchem velo tashchit
et pe'at zekanecha. זקנך. Zekanecha. Thank you.
זקנך. Zekanecha. זקניך Zekaneicha would be your elders, right? ולא תשחית את
פאת זקנך. Velo tashchit et pe'at zekanecha. מדשני קרא בדיבוריה, Midshani kra
bediburei, since the פסוק pasuk went out of its way, why did
it say ראשכם roshchem and then say זקנך? zekanecha? Why didn't it
say
זקניכם? zikneichem? זקנכם? zikanchem? Excuse me, I just did it again. Okay,
זקנכם, zikanchem, I guess it would be. Why did it say זקנך,
zekanecha, not זקנכם? zikanchem? מדשני קרא בדיבוריה Midshani kra bediburei and made
it the singular, דאי כתיב נכתוב רחמנא פאת זקנכם, d'itkeiv nichtav rachmana
pe'at zikanchem, מאי זקנך? mai zekanecha? זקנך zekanecha ולא זקן אשתך. v'lo
zikan ishtecha. It's singular. Your beard, not your wife's beard, okay? So
the singular to me is the smaller audience. The bearded lady. So
therefore the beard is only by men that naturally have a beard
and therefore if that's only by men the whole פסוק pasuk is
only by men as well as the פאות. pe'ot. Interesting, how do
you know that ראשכם roshchem then is not a different thing? ראשכם,
roshchem, men and women? I know, so it's funny. The ראשכם roshchem
is plural, you could say דווקא davka it's making it more broad
and we're choosing to link it to the end of the פסוק.
pasuk. What can I tell you? Again, it gets to the question
of how much do we know this or how much are we
deriving it? So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. ולא, V'lo,
are you telling me that women are not prohibited about cutting the
beard if they have a beard? והתניא, Vehatanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, braita, זקן אשה zikan isha or a סריס, saris, if a
woman or a eunuch has a beard, also because it would be
unlikely for a eunuch to have facial hair,
שהעלו שיער, shehe'elu sear, if they have facial hair, הרי הן כזקן
לכל דבריהם. harei hen kezakan l'chol divreihem. That's like a beard for
all purposes. So presumably all purposes means for the הלכה halacha of
cutting the beard. So at least that ברייתא, braita, I mean that's
not a question of the פסוקים psukim we're learning it from, that's
just a ברייתא braita that seems to go against our משנה. mishna.
Our משנה mishna says women are exempt and this ברייתא braita says
that if women have a beard, the beard has like has a
full status of a beard. So it's a סברא svara and מקרא
mikra that's now מסורה. masora. Right,
but the point is, it's funny that it's being brought in as
a challenge to the פסוקים psukim we derive it from because really
it's just a different opinion than our משנה. mishna. So why don't
you just say, okay, fine, they argue on our משנה, mishna, we're
defending our משנה. mishna. But let's see what the גמרא Gemara does
with it. So, מאי
לאו להשחתה? mai lav l'hashchata? So doesn't that mean for this prohibition
of cutting the hair of the beard? אמר אביי Amar Abaye no.
להשחתה לא
מצית אמרת. L'hashchata lo matzit amret. No, no, no, it can't be
talking about השחתה. hashchata. Because our משנה mishna is certainly right about
השחתה hashchata that women are exempt from cutting the beard. How do
you know? Besides the פסוקים psukim we quoted before, אביי Abaye is
going to give us another פסוק pasuk that teaches us that women
are exempt from cutting the beard. ויליף פאת פאת מבני אהרן, V'yalif
pe'at pe'at mibnei Aharon,
מה להלן נשים פטורות אף כאן נשים פטורות. ma halan nashim pturot
af kan nashim pturot. Now what you have to know is the
תורה Torah says both by ישראל Yisrael don't cut the פאות pe'ot
and the beard and by the כהנים, Kohanim, right? By the ישראל
Yisrael the תורה Torah says,
what's the פסוק pasuk we just had? לא תקפו פאת ראשכם
ולא תשחית את פאת זקנך. Lo takifu pe'at roshchem v'lo tashchit et
pe'at zekanecha. Okay? So that's by ישראל. Yisrael. By the כהנים Kohanim
it says, what does it say by the כהנים? Kohanim?
ראשכם? roshchem? No, it says, what's the פסוק pasuk by the
כהנים? Kohanim? ופאת זקנם לא יגלחו, u'f'at zekanam lo yigaleichu, so that's
the end of the
פסוק, pasuk, ופאת זקנם לא יגלחו. u'f'at zekanam lo yigaleichu.
What's the beginning of the פסוק? pasuk?
Anybody have the פסוקים psukim there? Here.
Thank you.
So the פסוק pasuk is 21.
No, it's ויקרא Vayikra 21. Oh, yeah, that's a different two.
Yeah, it's two פסוקים. psukim. So which one is it? Where is
it?
Here we go. לא יקחו ופאת זקנם, u'f'at zekanam no, no, it's
just לא יקחו קרחה. There's no פאת ראש. pe'at rosh. It's
לא יקרחו קרחה בראשם. lo yikrechu karcha b'rosham. Okay, לא יקרחו קרחה
בראשם. lo yikrechu karcha b'rosham. Okay, so anyway, at least the ופאת
זקנם is the same by both. Except here it's לא תשחית lo
tashchit and here it's לא יגלחו lo yigaleichu and we'll look at
that in a minute. But nevertheless, since this is talking about the
כהנים בני אהרן, Kohanim bnei Aharon, the פסוק pasuk says, right, that's
how the פסוקים psukim begin over there in אמור, Emor, the כהנים
בני אהרן, Kohanim bnei Aharon, we say since this is only men
and this is ופאת זקנם לא יגלחו, u'f'at zekanam lo yigaleichu, so
the פאת פאת pe'at pe'at links us, right, and tells us that
this is also only men and if this is also only men
then the whole thing is only men. So it's another basis to
tell us that this is talking about men. First we said it's
a סברא svara or זקנך zekanecha tells you that, now we're telling
us the link to כהן kohen tells it it's only men. יישר
כח. Yasher koach. Okay, so we'll see in a minute what אביי
Abaye does with this ברייתא braita that says a woman's beard is
treated equally like a beard, but he starts by saying there's no
question that women are exempt from this issue of shaving the beard.
Okay, so he says like this, he says, אביי אמר
אביי להשחתה לא מצית אמרת. Abaye amar Abaye, l'hashchata lo matzit amret.
You cannot say that women are prohibited about cutting the beard. They
are exempt from השחתה. ashchasa. Or חייב chayav in השחתה. ashchasa. ואליף
פאת פאת מבני אהרן, Vyalif pas pas mibnei Aharon, you learn it
from בני אהרן. bnei Aharon. מה להלן נשים פטורות אף כאן נשים
פטורות. Mah lehalan nashim pturos af kan nashim pturos. The same way
their women are exempt, here women are exempt. Now the גמרא Gemara
interrupts אביי Abaye to confuse it, okay, to get us a little
bit confused, so get ready. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
It says, how do we know that women are exempt by the
case of the כהנים? Kohanim? Because the פסוקים psukim started earlier than
that. Right? The פסוקים psukim started with,
where's the פסוקים? psukim? I'm sorry. It says like this. It says
אמור אל הכהנים בני אהרן, Emor el hakohanim bnei Aharon, right? לנפש
לא יטמא בעמיו. Lenefesh lo yitama beamav. So way back here, way
back three פסוקים psukim earlier was אמור אל הכהנים, Emor el hakohanim,
אל הכהנים בני אהרן. el hakohanim bnei Aharon. That's the
men, right? לנפש לא
יטמא בעמיו. Lenefesh lo yitama beamav. לא יטמא בעמיו. Lo yitama beamav.
כי אם לשארו הקרוב אליו, Ki im lish'ero hakaroiv eilav, and all
of this was טומאה. tuma. לא יטמאו, Lo yitmu, right? And it
ended with לא יטמא בעל בעמיו. lo yitama baal beamav. לא יטמא
בעל
בעמיו. lo yitama baal beamav. להחלו. lehachalo.
Then it says לא יקרחו קרחה בראשם. Lo yikrchu karcha beroshom. So
the question is how do we know this is only males? Because
way back here, it said we're talking about the men by טומאה.
tuma. Okay? So now the גמרא Gemara is going to stop to
question אביי Abaye and says your idea that you can learn from
כהנים Kohanim assumes that this label of men applies all the way
over here. How do you know that's true? So let's take a
look.
So it says like this. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אי סבירא
לן דכי כתיב בני אהרן אכולה עניינא כתיב. I sevira lan dechi
ksiv bnei Aharon akula inyana ksiv. Wait
a minute. If בני אהרן bnei Aharon applies to
the whole עניין, inyan, going all the way from טומאה tuma to
here,
why do I need a גזירה שוה? gzaira shava? You אביי Abaye
said that we make a גזירה שוה. gzaira shava. Forget גזירה שוה.
gzaira shava. I'll say this is all talking about men and I'll
apply this to ישראל Yisrael by a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. What's
the קל וחומר? kal vachomer? And I'll say like this, ותיתי בקל
וחומר, Vesaysi b'kal vachomer, ואנא מינא, V'ana mina, I would say, ומה
כהנים שריבה בהם הכתוב מצות יתירות, u'mah kohanim sheriba bahem haksav mitzvos
yesiros, of כהנים Kohanim that have greater obligations, more demands than a
normal ישראל, Yisrael, בני אהרן ולא בנות אהרן bnei Aharon velo bnos
Aharon when it comes to shaving the beard, it's only the sons,
only the men. ישראל לא כל שכן? Yisrael lo kol shekein? When
it comes to shaving the beard for ישראל, Yisrael, certainly it should
only be the men. So the גמרא Gemara is saying why do
you need your גזירה שוה? gzaira shava? Let's just learn it from
a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אי
לאו גזירה שוה, I lav gzaira shava, הוה אמינא. hava amina. So
this is still אביי's Abaye גזירה שוה. gzaira shava. If it wasn't
for the גזירה שוה, gzaira shava, I would have said הפסיק העניין.
hifsik hainyan. I would have said this is why says אביי Abaye
I need the גזירה שוה gzaira shava because I would have said
בני אהרן bnei Aharon doesn't apply. בני אהרן bnei Aharon is only
by טומאה. tuma. I would have said that maybe this is men
and women. But then, okay, maybe this applies to women equally. But
then I say wait, wait, but there's a גזירה שוה. gzaira shava.
If this applied to women equally, why would I need the גזירה
שוה? gzaira shava? What's the גזירה שוה gzaira shava teaching me? So
since the גזירה שוה gzaira shava is telling me there's something to
learn from כהן Kohen to
ישראל, Yisrael, the only thing there would be to learn is to
limit it to men. And therefore that teaches me that this is
going on the whole thing, okay? So I'm saying like this, if
I didn't have a גזירה שוה, gzaira shava, I would have said
this is men,
this is men and women,
הפסיק העניין, hifsik hainyan, and I wouldn't have had a קל וחומר
kal vachomer because I would have just said
this limit of men doesn't go this far, okay? But then comes
along a קל וחומר kal vachomer and a קל וחומר kal vachomer
says hey, you know what, there's something you can learn from one
to the other. I'm saying what can I learn? You know, this
is men and women, that's men and women, there's nothing to learn.
Oh! The fact that it's telling me there's something to learn teaches
me that this all is about men. And therefore then now I
understand why there's a גזירה שוה gzaira shava to teach me that
there's something to learn. Okay? So it's a very complicated גמרא Gemara
because at the end of the day, the גמרא Gemara isn't questioning
the idea that you can learn from כהן Kohen to ישראל Yisrael
that it's only men. The גמרא's Gemara just saying why did you
need the גזירה שוה? gzaira shava? Because if I didn't have the
גזירה שוה, gzaira shava, I would have said this applies equally to
women and whatever. The גזירה שוה gzaira shava forces me to find
something to learn and that teaches me that the idea of men
applies here as well. It's a literary sidebar, it's really about a
hermeneutics, exactly, which is I think sometimes hard to keep focus on.
But let's finish the argument, okay? So the גמרא Gemara says like
this,
השתא נמי נימא הפסיק העניין. Hashta nami nima hifsik hainyan. גמרא Gemara
says no, I disagree. If you would have said that this men
is only this part and this is men and women, I could
still learn something from the גזירה שוה gzaira shava even if this
is men and women. What could I learn from the גזירה שוה?
gzaira shava?
The גמרא Gemara says,
ואי משום גזירה שוה אי אמרת מה. V'i mishum gzaira shava i
amret mah. What's this? If it's about men and women, what's the
גזירה שוה? gzaira shava? shavah to teach me, there's a lot to
teach me to link the two. מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, Miba'ilei l'khade tanya,
like we taught in the ברייתא, braita, לא יגלחו. Lo yigalchu. And
now we're going to say, you know why you need the גזירה
שוה? gezeirah shavah? Forget the men issue. You need the גזירה שוה
gezeirah shavah to tell me what is the nature, what type of
act is forbidden? And here's what we're going to say. תשחית Tashchit
means a destructive act, like it gets it at the root. But
it doesn't mention shaving, it doesn't mention cutting. So תשחית tashchit could
be something like, you know, plucking it out with a tweezers. Because
now לא יגלחו lo yigalchu is a cutting and a shaving with
a blade, but that doesn't mean that it doesn't talk about getting
it out at the root. So each one of those is only
a piece of the פסוק. pasuk. So let's take a look. לא
יגלחו, Lo yigalchu, do not shave. יכול יגלחו במספרים יהא חייב, Yakhol
yigalchu b'misparayim yei chayav, so maybe you can't even cut with a
scissors, because that's a form of blade and cutting? תלמוד לומר לא
תשחית. Talmud lomar lo tashchit. No, תשחית tashchit tells me it has
to be a destructive cutting. It has to be like a shaving
against the skin. Cutting with scissors is a יגלחו yigalchu but it's
not a בל תשחית. bal tashchit. יכול ילקטו במלקט וברהיטני? Yakhol yilketu
b'malket u'v'rahitani? Oh,
but if it's about destructive and getting at the root, maybe plucking
it out with tweezers יהא חייב? yei chayav? תלמוד לומר לא יגלחו.
Talmud lomar lo yigalchu. No, no, לא תשחית lo tashchit isn't enough,
it has to be with a blade, it has to be with
shaving. הכיצד? Ha'keitzad? So what is the only thing that's prohibited? This
is very important. This is how we know, you know, this is
why many people think you can use a electric shaver because they
say an electric shaver is essentially a scissors action, right? So therefore,
הכיצד גילוח שיש בו השחתה. Ha'keitzad giluach sheyesh bo hashchatah.
It's only a shaving that cuts at the root. הוי אומר זה
תער, Havei omer zeh ta'ar, that's a razor blade. So you need
a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah to tell you the fundamental definition of
what type of shaving is forbidden on the beard. Not scissors, not
plucking, only like a razor blade shaving. So back to the question,
which is is that how do you know is that, you know,
why is אביי Abaye using this גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah to say
men or whatever? Again, this is just really like a hermeneutic question.
Why not just say that this applies straight and learn it out
from like a קל וחומר? kal v'chomer? So the גמרא Gemara says
no, אם כן נכתוב קרא את שבזקנך. im kein nikhtov kra et
she'be'zekanekha. מה פאת זקנך? Ma pe'at zekanekha? שמע מינה תרתי. Shma mina
tarti. If that was true that the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah was
not teaching me also the issue about men, it would have just
said לא תשחית את שבזקנך lo tashchit et she'be'zekanekha or את שבזקנך.
et she'be'zekanekha.
The fact that it had this extra word seems to be that's
the word פאת pe'at is coming to tell me use that extra
word to make a to learn out something else, to make a
גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah to teach me also this issue about not
just the nature of בל תשחית bal tashchit and יגלחו, yigalchu, but
also the idea that it's only men. Anyway, that was pretty complicated,
but the bottom line is what אביי Abaye is saying is that
I know בל תשחית bal tashchit is only men because it's only
men by כהנים kohanim and therefore either a קל וחומר kal v'chomer
or גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, and a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah maybe
teaches me other things as well. But bottom line is I know
this is men and therefore I apply it to ישראל Yisrael and
therefore it's clear that women are not obligated in the shaving of
the beard. So now we have to get back to the ברייתא
braita that said the beard by women is treated as a beard.
So let's just get back to that. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this:
ועל הא דתניא, ve'al ha d'tanya, that's what we taught in a
ברייתא, braita, זקן האשה והסריס שהעלו שיער הרי הן כזקן לכל דבריהם,
Zekan ha'ishah ve'ha'saris she'he'elu sei'ar harei hen k'zakan l'khol divreihem, it's considered
like a full beard. So the גמרא Gemara says למאי הלכתא? L'mai
hilkhata? For what הלכה? halakha? אמר מר זוטרא לטומאת נגעים. Amar Mar
Zutra l'tumat nega'im. To tell you that if it gets a spot
of צרעת, tzara'at, like we just learned, that they're טמא. tamei. So
the גמרא Gemara says טומאת נגעים בהדיא כתיב. Tumat nega'im b'hedya ketiv.
It says in the פסוק pasuk ואיש או אשה כי יהיה בו
נגע בראש או בזקן. Ve'ish o ishah ki yihyeh bo nega b'rosh
o b'zakan. It says זקן zakan even in the פסוק pasuk talking
about אשה. ishah. אלא אמר מר זוטרא לטהרת נגעים. Ella amar Mar
Zutra l'taharat nega'im.
No, no, to tell you that if the spot becomes actually that
when they become טהור tahor from this process of the טומאה tumah
of the hair, of the beard or of the head, that they
follow the same procedure as a man would be. So the גמרא
Gemara says טהרת נגעים נמי פשיטא. Taharat nega'im nami peshita. כיון דבת
טומאה היא, Keivan d'bat tumah hi, if she's going to be in
the category of becoming טמאה tmeiah just like the man, בת טהרה
היא. bat taharah hi. So she follows the same process of
טהרה. taharah. איצטריך. Itztarikh. Meaning איצטריך, itztarikh, not טהרה, taharah, back to
טומאה. tumah. Why do you need this ברייתא braita to teach me
that נגעים nega'im applies to the beard even if it's in a
פסוק? pasuk? סלקא דעתך אמינא לצדדין כתיב. Salka da'atakh amina l'tzadin ketiv.
Meaning, I would have read the פסוק, pasuk, and I probably would
have read the פסוק pasuk this way. If I said to you,
hey Charlie, it says ואיש או אשה כי יהיה בו נגע בראש
או בזקן. Ve'ish o ishah ki yihyeh bo nega b'rosh o b'zakan.
Is the תורה Torah talking about a beard for a woman? So
you would have said no, no, it means if a man or
a woman has a has a צרעת tzara'at in the head, or
a man has a spot on his beard. Right? You would have
said זקן zakan is referring to the case of man. You would
have said it's not talking about the case of women.
Yeah, the פסוק pasuk is only talking about about partially, it's the
it's on half of the פסוק. pasuk. איש או אשה כי יהיה
בו נגע בראש, Ish o ishah ki yihyeh bo nega b'rosh,
period, that's איש או אשה ish o ishah goes on בראש, b'rosh,
או בזקן, o b'zakan, or on a man's beard. So that's how
I might have read the פסוק. pasuk. הדר אתא לאיש, Hadar ata
l'ish, that beard goes to the man. קא משמע לן. Ka mashma
lan. So it teaches me not that way, it teaches... the ברייתא
*braitah* that it's considered the same for צרעת *tzara'at* for even a
צרעת *tzara'at* on the beard. So rather than say that there's a
ברייתא *braitah* that argues on our משנה *mishnah* and I don't know
why the גמרא *Gemara* can't contemplate that there's another opinion that argues
on the משנה *mishnah*, it says that everybody agrees a woman is
exempt from בל תשחית *bal tashchit* by the beard and the פאות
*pe'ot* and that the only issue is and the ברייתא *braitah* is
talking about the הלכה *halacha* of צרעת *tzara'at* on the beard just
to clarify what the פסוק *pasuk* means. How do you know a
woman is exempt? Either זקנך *zekanecha* not זקנכם *zekanechem* teaches you that,
or it's a סברא *sevara*, or the link to כהנים *kohanim* teaches
you that this is all talking about men and not women. Yes?
I just want to say I think it's really this concept of
פסיק עניינא *pesik inyana* is really interesting. Question: like where does the
context of the text end? How far can you extend and define
the context? Right, and it gets carried even more to the פסוק
*pasuk* we just dealt with, which is even in one פסוק *pasuk*
to limit it to half the פסוק *pasuk* and not the other.
Exactly, right. Okay, let's just read a little bit more. Look at
this, aren't we impressed about how we're totally back on track? Okay,
so the גמרא *Gemara* says: איסי תני
*Isi tani*, so now איסי *Isi* teaches: אף בל יקרחו נשים פטורות
*Af bal yikar'chu nashim peturot*. Women are not only exempt in the
shaving of the beard and of the sidelocks, but לא יקרחו קרחה
בראשם *lo yikrechu korcha berosham*, making like a bald spot in the
head, women are exempt. מאי טעמא *Mai ta'ama*? Okay, דאיסי דדרש הכי
*de-Isi de-darsh hachi*: בנים אתם לה' אלהיכם לא תתגדדו ולא תשימו קרחה
בין עיניכם למת *Banim atem l'Hashem Elokeichem lo titgodedu velo tasimu korcha
bein eineichem lamet*. Okay, so here, so here's another פסוק *pasuk* you've
got, right? By the כהן *kohen* you have this פאת זקנם לא
יגלחו *pe'at zekanam lo yigaleichu* that links to this פסוק *pasuk* by
ישראל *Yisrael*, but it also says לא יקרחו קרחה בראשם ופאת זקנם
לא יגלחו *lo yikrechu korcha berosham u-ve'at zekanam lo yigaleichu* and we
might as well say ובשרם לא ישרטו שרטת *uvisaram lo yisretu saretet*,
לא ישרטו שרטת *lo yisretu
saretet*. So from this link we learn what is the nature of
בל *bal*? It's a תשחית *tashchit* and a יגלחו *yigaleichu*. But these
things, קרחה בראשם *korcha berosham* and שרטת *saretet*, we have another פסוק
*pasuk* by ישראל *Yisrael*. What is the פסוק *pasuk* we have by
ישראל *Yisrael*? בנים אתם לה' אלהיכם *Banim atem l'Hashem Elokeichem*, בנים אתם
לה' אלהיכם *banim atem l'Hashem Elokeichem*, לא *lo*, what is it? לא
תתגדדו *lo titgodedu*, תתגדדו *titgodedu*, ולא תשימו קרחה בין עיניכם למת *velo
tasimu korcha bein eineichem lamet*. So this idea of making
lacerations in the flesh or bald spots over a dead body, right,
does that apply only to men and women? Why not? This פסוק
*pasuk*, there's nothing to limit this פסוק *pasuk* to men. בנים ולא
בנות *Banim velo banot*? Could be בנים *banim*. Anyway, but so presumably
this applies to men and women. Comes along איסי *Isi* and איסי
*Isi* says even the idea of קרחה *korcha* here only applies to
men. Where does he get that from? Let's just read one sentence
and we'll pick up with this on Shabbos. It says: מאי טעמא
דאיסי דדרש הכי בנים אתם לה' אלהיכם לא תתגדדו ולא תשימו קרחה
בין עיניכם למת כי עם קדוש אתה לה' אלהיך *Mai ta'ama de-Isi
darsh hachi banim atem l'Hashem Elokeichem lo titgodedu velo tasimu korcha bein
eineichem lamet ki am kadosh atah l'Hashem Elokecha*. And as Dov correctly
anticipated: בנים ולא בנות לקרחה *Banim velo banot le-korcha*. So the bald
spot and presumably maybe also the lacerations of the flesh presumably are
only for men, not for women. Okay, now but the גמרא *Gemara*
says: would you apply that to the lacerations? אתה אומר לקרחה או
אינו אלא לגדידה *Atah omer le-korcha o eino ela le-gedida*? Maybe the
lacerations also women can is only limiting it to men? No, כשהוא
אומר כי עם קדוש אתה לה' אלהיך *kshe-hu omer ki am kadosh
atah l'Hashem Elokecha*, you're a holy people, הרי גדידה אמור *harei gedida
emur*. So I mean, holy people, all of you are a holy
people. עם קדוש אתה *Am kadosh atah*. So that means don't make
lacerations. המני מקיים בנים ולא בנות *Hamani mekayem banim velo banot*? Something
that is less of an affront to the body, less of a
problem, which is only לקרחה *le-korcha*. Okay, ומה ראית לרבות את
הגדידה *u-mah re'ita le-rabot et ha-gedida*? Why do you say women are
included for the עם קדוש *am kadosh* in the prohibition of laceration
ולהוציא את הקרחה *u-le-hotzi et ha-korcha* but they're excluded from the bald
spot because it's בנים ולא בנות *banim velo banot*? מרבה אני את
הגדידה שישנה במקום שער ובלא במקום שער *Marbeh ani et ha-gedida she-yeshnah
bemakom sa'ar velo bemakom sa'ar* because גדידה *gedida* is a broader scope.
גדידה *Gedida* applies to any part of the body whether there's hair,
whether there's no hair, any lacerations. ומוציא אני את הקרחה שאינה אלא
במקום שער *U-motzi ani et ha-korcha she-einah ela bemakom sa'ar*. Okay, so
let's and but as opposed to קרחה *korcha* that's a more limited
prohibition, that's what we'll exclude women. So you have בנים *banim*, בנים
אתם לה' אלהיכם *banim atem l'Hashem Elokeichem*, and then you have כי
עם קדוש *ki am kadosh*. You could also say by the way,
okay, עם קדוש *am kadosh* is linked most immediate— no actually it
doesn't work. Anyway, so בנים *banim* we're going to say women are
excluded and included. They're excluded from the more limited prohibition of קרחה
*korcha* and they're included from the broader prohibition of lacerations in the
flesh. Okay, and we'll pick up on Shabbos with this position of
איסי *Isi*.